SAMUEL CARLEIAL FERNANDES

DOCTOR OF NATURAL SCIENCES



Birth: 26/07/1984, Fortaleza, Brazil

Nationality: Brazilian

Visa: residence permit (Germany)

Status: lives with partner and children

Address: Klingenbergstr. 8, Konstanz, Germany

Phone: +49 0151 2211 8568

Website: https://samuel-carleial.github.io/

Email: samuel.carleial.fernandes@protonmail.com

Objective

I have always been very keen to learn about the world and acquire knowledge. Due to my Brazilian roots, I decided to become a biologist, so that I could understand the natural world and make important discoveries. After several years of experience, however, I noticed that the human component has unquestionably a crucial part in my plan of being a scientist. Today, I want to engage in work that I am passionate about, but also that is meaningful and has an impact in society. After my experience in science I am open to learn new things and to have experience in other work environments.

Last position

05/2023 - now **Project Manager** at EuroNatur Foundation, Radolfzell, Germany

01/2022 - 02/2023 Paternity leave

08/2017 - 12/2021 Post-Doctoral Researcher, Clinical and Neuropsychology, University of Konstanz, Germany

Education

04/2013 - 07/2017 PhD in Biological Sciences (Dr. rer. nat.), University of Konstanz, Germany

in association with the Max Planck Research School for Organismal Biology (IMPRS), Germany

supervisors: Dr. Marc Stift and Dr. Mark van Kleunen

<u>dissertation</u>: The early steps of plant mating system evolution

grade: cum laude

01/2009 - 07/2011 MSc. in Biological Sciences (Systematics), National Autonomous University of Mexico, Mexico

supervisor: Dr. Alfonso Delgado-Salinas

<u>thesis</u>: Floral biology of Aeschynomene amorphoides

grade: honorific mention

01/2002 - 02/2007 BSc. & Lic. in Biological Sciences, Federal University of Ceará, Brazil

supervisor: Dr. Christian Westerkamp

thesis: Why are the nectaries in oiticica plants so large and oblique?

grade: 8759 I.R.A. (Brazilian grade)

Awards & Grants

04/2021	Research Seed Capital (RiSC), MKW Baden-Württemberg and University of Konstanz; 99,990.40 €
03/2019	Young Scholar Fund (YSF), University of Konstanz; amount: 6,330 €
06/2018	Independent Research Grant (Zukunftskolleg), University of Konstanz; 4,740 €
2013 - 2017	Stipend for doctoral studies (CNPq and Max Planck Institute); 1,365 € per month (4 years)
2009 - 2011	Stipend for master's degree (CONACYT); 7,000 MXN per month (2 years)
2005 – 2006	Stipend for bachelor's degree (PIBIC/UFC); 300 R\$ per month (1 year)

Research experience

08/2017 - 12/2021 Post-Doctoral Researcher, Clinical and Neuropsychology, Elbert Lab, University of Konstanz, Germany

<u>projects</u>: Narrative exposure therapy for traumatised offenders in North Kivu, Effect of narrative exposure therapy versus treatment as usual: a randomized controlled trial in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, amongst others <u>activities</u>: data management and analysis, statistical modelling, student supervision, scientific research,

project management, funding acquisition, international collaboration

12/2015 - 01/2016 Volunteer, HONKO Mangrove Conservation & Education, Madagascar

<u>activities</u>: data management, fieldwork data collection, maintenance of research station

03/2011 - 11/2011 **Technical Support Researcher** (100%) (REFLORA/CNPg) at the RON Herbarium, UNIR, Brazil

project: Mangrove long-term monitoring and sustainable livelihoods (2 weeks)

<u>project</u>: Integration, qualification and provision of data related to botanical collections in the Brazilian Amazon

activities: use of Brahms software, processing and management of botanical specimens, fieldwork

Teaching experience

12/2019 **Teaching** in course *Análise de dados em R* (16h), UFC, Brazil

10/2015 - 11/2015 **Teaching assistant** in course *Plant physiology* (60h), University of Konstanz, Germany 10/2014 - 11/2014 **Teaching assistant** in course *Plant physiology* (60h), University of Konstanz, Germany

03/2011 - 10/2011 Assistant professor at distance education in course Biology, UNIR, Brazil

04/2006 - 12/2006 Teaching assistant in courses Botany and Plant anatomy and morphology, UFC, Brazil

Training

10/2021 (5 days) Epigenomics Data Analysis: from Bulk to Single Cell, National Bioinformatics Infrastructure Sweden (NBIS)

04/2021 (4 days) Structural Equation Modelling in R, University of Cambridge

12/2020 (5 days) Introduction to Analysis of Epigenetic Data, UCDavis Bioinformatics Core

03/2017 - 09/2018 Data Analyst Nanodegree, Udacity

12/2014 | 12/2015 Introduction to Geometric Morphometrics | Geometric Morphometrics in R, Transmitting Science

Skills

Stat. analyses common statistical methods, data modeling, data visualization

Programming R (mostly) and proficient with python, bash, SQL, html

Software Microsoft Office, LaTeX, Inkscape, SPSS, Jupyter Notebooks, Tableau **Other** scientific article and project writing, vector image editing, version control

General interests

Nature (hiking, sightseeing), sports (cycling, climbing, swimming), reading (news and books), music (rock).

Languages

Portuguese native

EnglishfluentTOEFL: 102/120 (year 2011)GermanproficientGoethe Institute: B2.2 (year 2013)SpanishfluentEPLE/UNAM: 830/1000 (year 2008)

Publications

Schmitt S, Robjant K, Elbert T, Chibashimba A, Hoeffler A, Carleial S, Koebach A (2022). **Breaking the cycles of violence with** narrative exposure: **Development and feasibility of NETfacts, a community-based intervention for populations living under continuous threat**. PLoS ONE, 17(12): e0275421

Robjant K, et al. (2022). **NETfacts: An integrated intervention at the individual and collective level to treat communities affected by organized violence**. PNAS, 119(44): e2204698119

Carleial S, Soares M (2022). The urgent and yet forgotten problems of current scientific and academic practice. Arquivos de Ciências do Mar, ISSN 2526-7639

Carleial S, Nätt D, Unternaehrer E, Elbert T, Robjant K, Wilker S, Vukojevic V, Kolassa IT, Zeller AC, Koebach A (2021) **DNA** methylation changes following Narrative Exposure Therapy in a randomized controlled trial with female former child soldiers. Sci Rep, 11(1), 18493

Abreu L, et al. (2021) Life with corona: increased gender differences in aggression and depression symptoms due to the COVID-19 pandemic burden in Germany, Front Psychol, 12: 689396

Koebach A, Carleial S, Elbert T, Schmitt S, Robjant K (2021) **Treating trauma and aggression with Narrative Exposure Therapy in former child and adult soldiers: a randomized controlled trial in Eastern DR Congo**, J Consult Clin Psychol, 89(3), 143-155

Serpeloni F, Narrog JA, de Assis SG, Avanci JQ, Carleial S, Koebach A (2021) Narrative Exposure Therapy versus treatment as usual in a sample of trauma survivors who live under ongoing threat of violence in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil: study protocol for a randomised controlled trial. Trials, 22(1), 1-10

Unternaehrer E, Carleial S, Koebach A, Zeller A, Meinlschmidt G, Elbert T (2020) **Association between BDNF DNA methylation and symptom improvement following cognitive-behavioral therapy in stress-related mental disorders**, Psychoneuroendocrinology, 119: 105009

Robjant K, Schmitt S, Chibashimba A, Carleial S, Elbert T, Koebach A (2020) **Trauma, aggression and post conflict perpetration of community violence in female former child soldiers** – a study in Eastern DR Congo. Front Psychiatry, 11:1-10

Robjant K, Koebach A, Schmitt S, Chibashimba A, Carleial S, Elbert T (2019) The treatment of posttraumatic stress symptoms and aggression in female former child soldiers using adapted Narrative Exposure therapy – a RCT in eastern democratic republic of Congo. Behavior Res Ther, 123: 103482

Carleial S, Maurel N, van Kleunen M, Stift M (2018) **Oviposition by the Mountain Alcon Blue butterfly increases with host plant flower number and host ant abundance**. Basic Appl Ecol, 28:87-96

Carleial S, van Kleunen M, Stift M (2017) Relatively weak inbreeding depression in selfing but also outcrossing populations of North American Arabidopsis lyrata, J Evol Biol, 30: 1994-2004

Carleial S, van Kleunen M, Stift M (2017) Small reductions in corolla size and pollen:ovule ratio, but no changes in flower shape in selfing populations of the North American Arabidopsis lyrata, Oecologia, 401-413

Tedder A, Carleial S, Golebiewska M, Kappel C, Shimizu KK, Stift M (2015) **Evolution of the selfing syndrome in Arabis alpina** (**Brassicaceae**), PloS ONE, 10(6): e0126618

Carleial S, Delgado-Salinas A, Domínguez CA, Terrazas T (2015) **Reflexed flowers in Aeschynomene amorphoides** (Fabaceae: Faboideae): a mechanism promoting pollination specialization? Bot J Linn Soc, 177(4): 657-666

Carleial S, Bigio NC (2014) What survived from the PLANAFLORO Project: angiosperms of Rondônia State, Brazil, Checklist, 10(1): 33-45

Peer-reviews

Am. J. Bot., AoB Plants, Aust. J. Bot., Check List, Epigenomics, PeerJ